we have Rob Gore Rob Gore hi Ravi and
imamo Rob Gore Rob Gore hi Ravi i
gang up Rob Gore and all viewers who
gang gore Rob Gore i sve gledaoce koji su
have been around for some time it is so
već neko vrijeme je bilo tako
nice to hear from you it's been a while
lepo je čuti od vas je to bilo neko vrijeme
and we've missed you and I hope you're
i nedostajali smo i nadam se da ste
doing well so thank you very much for
Dobro, hvala vam puno
reaching out to the show yes okay I have
Da saznam da je dobro
resized some images using the GIMP so
izmenio neke slike pomoću GIMP-a
that they are the same height not
da su iste visine ne
concerned if the width is different
zabrinuto ako je širina drugačija
I checked the images the image
Proverio sam slike slike
properties and made sure that they are
osobine i postarali se da su
all set to 400 pixels 400 pickles
sve postavljeno na 400 piksela 400 kiseli krastavci
pickles 411 for the height and the XY
kiseli krajevi 411 za visinu i XY
resolution is set to 72 pixels per inch
rezolucija je podešena na 72 piksela po inču
when saving the images I have used to
kada čuvate slike na koje sam navikla
save for web option with 90% quality
osim za web opciju sa 90% kvalitetom
when adding these images to my website
kada dodam ove slike na moju web stranicu
using WordPress they are showing a
koristeći WordPress oni pokazuju a
different height any ideas or
različite visine bilo koje ideje ili
suggestions yeah okay let's understand
Da, da, razumemo
the inner workings of how WordPress is
unutarnji rad o tome kako je WordPress
is treating your images I'm going to
tretira vaše slike koje idem
head over to pixels comm we're just
Pređite na pikselske komande
going to grab a real quick stock image
idem da uzmem stvarno brzu sliku
so like a whole line like a cardinal
tako da cijeli niz kao kardinal
when I just grab these clouds okay so
kada samo uhvatim ove oblake u redu
poofy makes you want to fly doesn't a
pufnastu čini želite da letite ne a
Henri
Henri
that's just like outside right now
to je baš kao i sada napolju
Robbie so you got to go yeah I'll just
Robi, pa moraš da ideš ja ću samo
throw that on my desktop for you here
baci to na moju radnu površinu za tebe ovde
Rob Gor okay so I'm going to take that
Rob Gor u redu tako da ću uzeti
photo and I'm going to make you know
fotografiju i upoznaću te
what I better grab a second photo here
šta bih bolje uhvatio drugu fotografiju ovde
as well because because I want to we
takođe zato što mi želimo
want to be able to demonstrate the
želite da demonstrirate
difference here's the perfect example
razlika je savršen primer
this one's super wide okay so that one's
ovaj je super širok, tako da je on jedan
a perfect one to use okay now we've got
savršen za korištenje ok, sada imamo
two pickles okay grab these photos let's
dva kikirika u redu pokupite ove fotografije
bring them up into the GNU image
unesite ih u GNU sliku
manipulation program okay so we see that
Program manipulacije je u redu, tako da to vidimo
and we see oh that's a big high-res
i vidimo da je to veliki rezolucionar
image from texels nice
lijepa slika iz Teksela
yeah you know it's a high-res image when
Da, znate da je slika visoke rezolucije kada
your system fades for a moment and like
vaš sistem nestaje na trenutak i voli
this window is not responding oh yes it
ovaj prozor ne odgovara da je to
is
je
like oh the lights flicker it's like you
Kao da su lampice treperljive, to je kao i vi
don't know how hard to download it love
ne znam koliko je teško downloadovati ljubav
it okay so here's image number one let's
to je u redu, evo ovde slika broj 1
choose our height we're going to say our
izaberite našu visinu koju ćemo mi reći
height is going to be 600 because if if
visina će biti 600, jer ako ako
I'm hearing this question correctly
Ovo pitanje pravilno čujem
rongeur is setting the height to a
rongeur postavlja visinu na a
static height so that it's the same for
statički visinu tako da je to isto
all his images right but he's not caring
sve njegove slike, ali on se ne brine
about the width correct okay so we're
o širini je u redu, pa smo
going to use 600 as our height so this
idemo da koristimo 600 kao našu visinu
one happens to end up as 393 with the
jedan se događa da završi kao 393 sa
width or the oh sorry no I
širina ili oh, izvinjavam se ne
Oh Jeremy just as I clicked it I
Oh Jeremy baš kao što sam kliknuo da mi
realized no that was actually backwards
nije shvatio da je to zapravo bilo unazad
its width and height now the GIMP has
njegova širina i visina sada ima GIMP
reversed things and now I have to wait
preokrenuti stvari i sad moram da sačekam
for this massive image to scale yet
za ovu masivnu sliku još uvek skali
again holy big image here guys we're
opet sveta velika slika ovde momci
looking at it
gledajući to
18.2% still there at least nighttime
18,2% još uvijek ima bar noću
yeah it's just kind argh this is the
Da, to je nekako argh ovo je
Halloween episode version oh come now
Verzija epizode Noć veštica oh, dođi sada
then you said why did I choose such a
onda ste rekli zašto sam izabrao takav
big image for you around 8 million maybe
velika slika za vas oko 8 miliona možda
I'm just gonna use thee what did the
Samo ću te iskoristiti šta je uradio
height end up being let's use that uh
visina završiti kao upotreba let da je uh
holy 400 pixels for the height because
Sveti 400 piksela za visinu, jer
we're live I would never do this I'm
živi u životu nikad ne bih to uradio
gonna force quit cuz I don't want you to
će na snagu otkaz jer sam ne htjeti
have to wait for me to look at a
moram sačekati da pogledam
progress indicator that's your deal go
napredak pokazatelj da je vaš posao ide
go what is this Microsoft Windows uh
idite šta je ovaj Microsoft Windows uh
totally no it's good here we go ok a
potpuno ne dobro je idemo OK
nice picture yeah that's a lovely
lepa slika da, to je divno
picture you're travelling it oh sorry go
sliku koju putujete to oh mi je go
guys alright let's grab height not yet
momci, hajde da ne uzmemo visinu
because you're doing it by height sorry
jer to radiš po visini izvini
I thought that that one was height for
Mislio sam da je to visina
some reason I don't know ok so I'm going
neki razlog zbog kojeg ne znam dobro, pa idem
to do 600 height and notice that it's
da uradite 600 visina i primetite da je to
locked proportionally so it's going to
zaključano proporcionalno, pa će to ići
rescale correctly and we're going to
rescale korektno i mi ćemo
scale it down
smanjite ga
so there is our image with 600 height
pa imamo našu sliku sa 600 visina
and it ends up with 916 width okay so
i završava se sa 916 širine u redu tako
I'm going to export as now you said you
Idem da izvezem, kao što si sada rekao
used save for web you must be in an
koristite sačuvati za web morate biti u
older version I'm going to export as and
stariju verziju koju ću izvesti kao i
I'm going to call this for web okay and
Ja ću zvati za web redu i
then we'll do the same as you did 90% I
onda ćemo učiniti isto kao i 90%
usually go for 98 because I'm a beast
obično idem na 98 jer sam zver
for quality okay
za kvalitet ok
600 quality 600 height is what we're
600 kvalitetnih 600 visina je ono što smo
going for image scale image 600 height
ide za skali slike 600 visine
so now I think if I follow your question
pa sad mislim da ako pratim vaše pitanje
that I am essentially now at the point
da sam u suštini sada na mestu
that you're at where you've created
da ste na mestu gde ste kreirali
these images you're not caring about the
o ovim slikama o kojima se ne brinete
width but the height is the same for all
ali visina je ista za sve
of your images so when I look at that
vaših slika, pa kad pogledam to
it's the same height as the other one so
to je iste visine kao onaj drugi tako
I'm going to export that as for web and
Izvoziću to kao za web i
again we're going to give it 90% quality
Opet ćemo ga dati kvalitet 90%
which is 10% compression Nagesh mm-hmm
što je 10% kompresije Nagesh mm-hmm
all right so we now have two new images
U redu, sada imamo dve nove slike
I'm going to throw those ones away so we
Obeći ću te one, pa mi
don't get confused for web I'm going to
nemojte se zbuniti za web koji idem
maximize that that's the size that's the
maksimalno da je to veličina, to je
size notice exactly the same height they
obaveštenje o veličini upravo iste visine
are both 600 pixels high beautiful
su visoki i 600 piksela prekrasna
WordPress is responsive it's the word of
WordPress je odgovoran to je reč od
the day so the whole idea behind
dan tako celu ideju
responsive design is that when I look at
Odzivan dizajn je to kada gledam
a website a wordpress site on my
sajt na stranici za WordPress
computer it's going to look great
kompjuter će izgledati odlično
the images are going to fill in the
slike će se popuniti
space it's going to look really nice if
prostor će izgledati zaista lepo ako
I look at it on my phone same thing it's
Gledam na svoj telefon ista stvar
just restructured and moved around
samo se restrukturirala i preselila
that's called responsive design so when
to se zove odgovoran dizajn, pa kada
you upload an image to WordPress it is
upload sliku na WordPress je
it's going to do scaling proportional
to će učiniti skaliranje proporcionalno
scaling based on its responsive layout
skaliranje zasnovano na svom odgovarajućem rasporedu
so that has to do with your template
tako da to ima veze sa tvojim šablonom
your theme and your settings in for
svoju temu i vaša podešavanja
multimedia in WordPress itself under and
multimedija u WordPressu pod i
I think it's general so with that said
Mislim da je to uopšte tako s tim, rekao je
when I upload this image it's going to
kada pošaljem ovu sliku koju će ići
get resized by WordPress to a responsive
dobijate veličinu od WordPressa na odgovarajući
size so let's bring them both up again
veličine pa ćemo ih dovesti ponovo
and usually how it's going to work is
i obično kako će na rad
it's going to have maximums so let's say
to će biti maksimum , recimo
our maximum is so WordPress thinks the
naš maksimum je tako da WordPress misli
maximum is 300 by 300 for this
maksimalno je 300 do 300 za ovo
particular allocation of the image so if
određena alokacija slike, pa ako
the maximum is 300 it's going to look at
maksimalno je 300 koji će se gledati
this image and it's going to go okay
ovu sliku i to će ići u redu
that means 300 width which is going to
to znači 300 širina koja će se desiti
result in a 197 height because if I make
rezultira visinom 197, jer ako napravim
it a 300 height the width is now over my
to je 300 visina, a sada mi je širina
maximum which is 300 so we have to do it
maksimalno 300, tako da to moramo učiniti
that way so this is what happens in the
tako da je to ono što se dešava u
background of WordPress so now we've got
background of WordPress, pa sada imamo
an image that is 300 by 197 take this
slika koja je 300 do 197 uzima ovo
other image use the same math and say
druga slika koristi istu matematiku i kaže
okay the maximum is 300 so if I put 300
u redu je maksimalno 300, ako stavim 300
as the height this is WordPress talking
jer visina je WordPress
now that's going to make it seven
sada će to učiniti sedam
hundred and seven width which is over my
stotinu i sedam širina koja je preko mene
maximum which is 300 so my width has to
maksimalno 300, tako da moja širina mora
become 300 so now the height because
postati 300 tako da je sada visina jer
this is proportional is now 127 pixels
ovo je proporcionalno sada 127 piksela
on that image so now I end up with an
na toj slici, tako da sada završim sa
image that is 300 by 127 it falls within
slika koja je 300 do 127, ona pada
the maximums the WordPress has
maksimumi koje ima WordPress
established for your layout but now we
ustanovljen za vaš izgled, ali sada smo
have one image that's 300 by 127 and one
ima jednu sliku od 300 do 127 i jednu
image that's 300 by 197 that's what's
sliku od 300 do 197 to je ono što je
happening there so if we want to have
tamo dešava pa ako želimo da imamo
our images be exactly the same every
naša slika biti isti svaki
time we need to have them be the same
vreme je da im budemo isti
the term that we're going to throw out
termin koji ćemo izbaciti
there is called aspect ratio so you've
tu se zove aspekt, tako da imate
heard of your TV is 16 over 9 so that
čuo je vaš TV 16 više od 9 tako da
can be 1920 by 1080 pixels but it can
može biti 1920 sa 1080 piksela, ali može
also be 1280 by 720 pixels it's the same
Takođe je 1280 do 720 piksela isto je isto
aspect ratio even though they're
aspekt odnos iako su
different sizes on your screen first
Prvo, na ekranu su različite veličine
example is 1080p second example 720p so
Primer je 1080p drugi primer 720p
in order to achieve that so if we know
kako bismo to postigli, ako to znamo
I'm going to just undo both of these so
Samo ću ih obojiti tako
that we're back to having a 600 height
da smo se vratili na 600 visina
so I'm going to look at this one and
pa ću pogledati ovo i
let's let's pretend that this is the
Hajde da se pretvaramo da je ovo
this is the perfect shape for our images
ovo je savršen oblik za naše slike
so we're going to call
pa ćemo pozvati
are shaped but it's the aspect ratio
su oblikovane, ali to je odnos aspekta
this is the the aspect ratio that we
ovo je odnos gledišta koji smo mi
want so the way that I can fix the other
želim tako kako mogu da popravim drugu
image so that it's the same aspect ratio
slike, tako da je isti odnos aspekta
is I can look at this one and I can go
da li mogu da pogledam ovaj i mogu ići
okay this is 9/16 by 600 so now go back
OK, ovo je 9/16 na 600 pa se sada vratite
to the other image which has already
na drugu sliku koja je već bila
been scaled down to 600 but now I need
smanjen je na 600, ali sada mi je potreban
to right-click and this time I'm going
da kliknem desnim klikom i ovog puta idem
to go image canvas size and I'm going to
da idem na platnu veličine slike i ja idem
change this so that it is not linked
promijeniti tako da nije povezan
make sure that these two are not linked
uverite se da ova dva nisu povezana
proportionally and I'm going to change
proporcionalno i promeniću se
this what did I say 9/16 was that
ovo je ono što sam rekao 9/16
correct right nobody made notes no 913
ispravan u pravu niko se bilješke ne 913
that's right okay image canvas size 9/16
to je u redu okom slike veličine 9/16
now you see what happened does it
sad vidite šta se desilo to radi
position that in such a way that it's
postavite to na takav način da je to
cutting off the right-hand side of the
odsiječe desne ruke
image so I can the left-hand side
tako da mogu na levu stranu
no the right-hand side yeah that's right
Ne, desno, da, tako je
so I can drag this you see that crop box
tako da mogu da povučem ovo što vidite u toj kutiji
that's the size that we're going for
to je veličina da ćemo za
9/16 by 600 so I can reposition this
9/16 do 600, tako da mogu repositionirati ovo
anywhere any way I like
bilo gde na bilo koji način volim
and then hit resize and what it's going
a zatim udari veličinu i šta se dešava
to do is it's going to crop that image
da uradi to će obrezati tu sliku
to the exact proportions
do tačnih proporcija
so now if I export that image and then
pa sada ako ja izvozim tu sliku i onda
close out of those now I can look at
Zatvorite od onih koje mogu sada da gledam
that image and look at the next image
tu sliku i pogledajte sledeću sliku
and they are exactly the same okay that
a oni su potpuno isti u redu da
is good that said what happens if you
je dobro što je rekao šta se događa ako ti
end if you start off with one that is
završite ako počnete sa onim što jeste
see I'm cropping and I'm scaling down to
vidim da se secam i da se sklanjam
600 remember that WordPress is going to
600 se seća da će WordPress ići
scale anyway so you don't necessarily
u svakom slučaju, ne morate nužno
have to scale it down to 600 first let
mora da ih skali do 600 prvih letova
WordPress do the dirty work for you so
WordPress rade prljavi posao za vas tako
if we have a high-resolution image let's
ako imamo sliku visoke rezolucije, hajde
grab one because now that we've learned
zgrabite ga zato što smo sada naučili
what we what we what we don't need to do
ono što mi mi ono što mi ne moramo učiniti
is scale the image we don't need to
je razmera koju ne trebamo
resize it so that it's 600 height
promenite veličinu tako da je 600 visina
instead once we know our desired aspect
umesto da znamo željeni aspekt
ratio and I just lost access to my mouse
i izgubio sam pristup mišu
again sometimes this happens on a boon
ponekad se to ponekad dešava na blagonaklonosti
to me
meni
and they are mattei and I think that it
i oni su mattei i to mislim
might have to do with the video drivers
možda ima veze sa video drajverima
I can get in there that way that works
Mogu da uđem tamo na način koji funkcioniše
now that I know that really what I'm
sada kada to znam stvarno ono što sam ja
looking for is the aspect ratio I don't
Traženje je razmera nečega
have to actually rescale this down to
moraju ustvari smanjiti ovo
600 hight I'm going to show you how to
600 visina ću vam pokazati kako
do this so here's my massive high-res
uradi ovo, evo moje velike rezolucije
image there it is so now if I go image
slika tamo je sada sada ako idem na sliku
canvas size notice I'm not going to
obaveštenje o veličini platna neću da idem
scale this to 600 first now what I'm
ovo prvo skaluram na 600, što sam ja
going to do is I'm going to copy the
Idem da kopiram
either width or height it's going to
bilo širinu ili visinu
vary depending on the original original
variraju u zavisnosti od originalnog originala
aspect ratio of the image so I'll show
aspekt omjer slike tako da ću pokazati
you the the process here and then you
ti proces ovde i tebi
can figure out which one is which for
može shvatiti za koju je za šta
your photo I'm going to copy the height
vašu fotografiju koju ću kopirati visinu
now I'm going to go 9/16 by 600 that's
sada idem na 9/16 na 600, to je
the aspect ratio that I'm desiring now I
prosječni odnos koji želim sada ja
can turn on the link that makes it so
možete uključiti na link koji čini tako
that it's proportional and then paste
da je proporcionalan, a zatim paste
back in the original height now I have a
vratio sam se u prvobitnu visinu sada imam
proportional aspect ratio crop for this
proporcionalna promena prosjeka za ovo
image that is 1847 high hit resize and
slika koja je veliku promenu veličine 1847 i
there's my image it's twenty eight
moj lik je dvadeset osam
twenty eighteen forty seven and yet it's
dvadeset osamnaest četrdeset sedam, a ipak jeste
exactly the same aspect ratio as my nine
upravo isti aspekt odnosa sa mojim devet
sixteen by six hundred image because of
Šesnaest za šest stotina slika zbog
the way that I processed that so Rob
način na koji sam tako obrađivao Roba
Gore I hope that that helps shed some
Gore Nadam se da to pomaže u odvajanju nekih
light on why it's happening how it's
svetlo o tome zašto se to dešava
happening and how to avoid it
i kako to izbjeći
use the highest resolution images that
koristiti najvišu slike rezoluciju koja
you can because WordPress is going to
možete jer WordPress ide
automatically scale those down for you
automatski skale one za vas
it's not like old-school web design
to nije kao web dizajn u staroj školi
where you had to scale it down because
gde ste morali da je smanjite, jer
it's too big
prevelika je
yeah save your save your image once it's
da sačuvajte svoju sliku kada je to u pitanju
ready do some touch-ups if you need to
spremni napraviti neke touch-up-ove ako trebate
but high res is great and then WordPress
ali visok res je sjajan, a onda WordPress
is going to shrink it down the only
će se smanjiti se jedino
reason you want to do it any other way
razlog zašto želite da to učinite na neki drugi način
is maybe if you have a very finite
možda je ako imate vrlo ograničen
amount of space on your server then you
količinu prostora na serveru, onda
might want to reduce the amount of space
možda bi želeli smanjiti količinu prostora
that's being consumed by your images by
koje vaše slike pokreću
rescaling but
preklapanje, ali
hopefully that helps
nadam se da to pomaže
[Music]
[Muzika]
[Applause]
[Aplauz]